<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the king, on the second Sunday in Advent, Decemb. viii, 1678 by Symon Patrick ...</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12588047</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12588047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63800</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56696)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63800)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 674:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the king, on the second Sunday in Advent, Decemb. viii, 1678 by Symon Patrick ...</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 41 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Macock for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XV, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63800:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63800:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Before the KING, ON THE Second SUNDAY in <hi>ADVENT, Decemb.</hi> viii. 1678.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>SYMON PATRICK,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Macock</hi> for <hi>R. Royſton</hi> Bookſeller to His moſt Sacred Majeſty. 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:63800:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63800:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED Before the KING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ROMANS xv. 4. beginning.</bibl>
               <q>For whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Holy Scriptures are ſo full a Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of all Divine Learning, and we are ſo frequently exhorted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair thither for our conſtant Inſtruction; that as there is no Excuſe for thoſe who would lock them up from the people of God, and not ſuffer them to look into them: ſo they are no leſs worthy to be condemned, who will not look into them when they may; nor take any care to enrich their minds with thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63800:3"/> Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge, which the Royal Pſalmiſt thought more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious than <hi>thouſands of Gold and Silver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To correct this Negligence, Our Church now calls upon us to pray in the Collect for this Second week in <hi>Advent,</hi> that we <hi>may in ſuch wiſe hear them, read, mark, learn, and inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly digeſt them, that by Patience and Comfort of his holy Word, we may embrace and ever hold faſt the bleſſed hope of Everlaſting life;</hi> which is infinitely more worth than all our preſent poſſeſſions in this World.</p>
            <p>Now that we may do according to our Prayers, <hi>mark</hi> I beſeech you the firſt words of the Epiſtle for this day, which I have now read unto you: in which the Apoſtle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to us the ſtudy of the holy Scriptures, from the Benefit we may receive by them; even by thoſe parts of them which may ſeem to you perhaps very barren, or little condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the Profit of Chriſtian People. For <hi>Firſt</hi> of all, we may learn ſomething, he tells us, for our Chriſtian Inſtruction, out of thoſe Scriptures which <hi>were written aforetime;</hi> in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient dayes, before the <hi>Advent</hi> or Coming of our Saviour Chriſt. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is to be met withall in every part of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63800:3"/> theſe ancient Writings; for he ſayes, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things</hi> were written heretofore, in the Sacred Volumes, were written for our learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. There is nothing unprofitable, nothing needleſs and ſuperfluous in them; but all tends to Edification. Nor were they written (you may further conſider in the <hi>Third</hi> place) for <hi>their</hi> Benefit alone who lived when they were written; but <hi>for our learning</hi> alſo, who live in the dayes of Chriſt. <hi>For whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our learning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the clearer underſtanding of all which Particulars, you may be pleaſed to obſerve, that theſe words ſeem to come in as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a tacit Objection, of ſuch as might fancy the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament did not appertain to Chriſtians, or contained nothing of Chriſt in them. For the Apoſtle had juſt before quoted a place out of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> and applyed it to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; <hi>Who did not pleaſe himſelf: but as it is written</hi> (Pſal. lxix. 9.) <hi>The reproaches of them that reproached thee, fell on me.</hi> And then (to prevent ſuch an Exception as I now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) immediately addes, <hi>For whatſoever
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63800:4"/> things were written afore time, were written for our learning.</hi> As if he had ſaid; Do not tell me that <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks there concerning himſelf: for, though that be true, He repreſented alſo a greater King than himſelf; and in ſuch words as thoſe Propheſied of the Reproaches and Perſecutions of Chriſt by the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, after the ſame manner that he ſuffered by <hi>Saul</hi> and his Servants.</p>
            <p>This plain declaration of the Apoſtle about the Scriptures written aforetime, ſhould have ſufficiently ſecured them, one would have thought, from all contempt; and preſerved a due Reverence towards them in the minds of all thoſe, who are called by the Name of Chriſt. But ſo deſirous the Malignant Spirit is, to have thoſe Holy Books thrown out of peoples hands; that he hath ſtirred up ſeveral Sects, who have not only aſperſed them, but utterly rejected them; as uſeleſs and unprofit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; nay dangerous and hurtful. In the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to whoſe Allegations I ſhall fully explain my Text; and ſhow how every part of thoſe Holy Books, which were written before Chriſts coming, contain ſomething for our learning and inſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63800:4"/>
            <p>And for our clearer proceeding, I think it will be neceſſary to obſerve, that the firſt Blaſphemers of the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament, were they who introduced the Doctrine of two Gods; one an Evil being, the God of the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> the other a good and gracious being, the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The Ringleader of theſe, in all probability, was <hi>Simon Magus</hi> the <hi>Samaritan;</hi> who was followed by a rabble of vile people, ſuch as <hi>Baſilides, Carpocras, Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus,</hi> and a number more whoſe names are not worth the remembring. Who, though they did not profeſs his Name, yet followed his opinion, as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> I. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</note> ſpeaks, <hi>For whoſoever they were,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that Adulterated the Truth and ſpoiled the Doctrine of the Church, they were all the Diſciples and ſucceſſors of this Man.</hi> No bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy doubts but the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> were; <hi>who are ſaid among the reſt of their Doctrines to have had this; of a Good God and an Evil God.</hi> They are the Words of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> VI. <hi>de Haereſ.</hi>
               </note> in the concluſion of the account he gives us of their Hereſie. Which was followed no doubt by <hi>Marcion, Apelles</hi> and their Diſciples; who openly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this, to the great ſcandal of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For from hence I ſuppoſe it was that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63800:5"/> 
               <hi>Celſus</hi> the Philoſopher took occaſion to charge Chriſtians with this deteſtable opinion; that they held <hi>an Execrable God</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the great God of all.</hi> But they cleared themſelves ſo well of this Crimination, in their admirable writings; that they neither left any colour for it, nor any conſiderable perſon that durſt maintain it. Till, not long before the dayes of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> there ſtarted up a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> whoſe ſurname was <hi>Manes:</hi> who follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other ancient Hereticks (as St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> words are <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap</hi> XLVI. <hi>de Hereſ.</hi>
               </note>) revived this Opinion, when it was in a manner dead and buried: and from him it was ever after called the Hereſie of the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees.</hi> Who held two firſt Co-eternal princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of all things, <hi>diverſe from, and adverſe to</hi> each other: (as he alſo ſpeaks) as oppoſite as Light and Darkneſs; the one a Good, the other an Evil Being.</p>
            <p>Now the Doctrine of theſe men concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Scriptures, was conformable to their firſt foul opinion concerning God: and may be comprehenped in theſe <hi>Five</hi> propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> they ſaid that <hi>the Writings of the Old Teſtament were from the Evil Principle;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> that they <hi>belong'd only to the Jews, not to Chriſtians;</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63800:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That they were <hi>not profitable for the Confirmation of Faith;</hi> nor,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> For <hi>the teaching good Manners;</hi> but rather deſtructive to them; And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That they <hi>contradicted the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>The folly of which, if I may have leave briefly to repreſent, it will be the cleareſt Explication I can give of theſe words of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and let you ſee how much we may learn, even out of the Scriptures which were written aforetime.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> of them [viz. <hi>That the Writings of the Old Teſtament were from the evil Principle,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> being dictated by bad Angels,] is ſuch a ſenceleſs Blaſphemy, that I ſhould have wholly omitted it; were it not for the reaſon now mentioned: that it gives a fair occaſion to ſhew, there is ſomething worth our learning even in ſuch Hiſtorical paſſages of the Old Scriptures, as ſeem leſs inſtructive. For S. <hi>Paul</hi> having plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that the Law and the Goſpel had the ſame Author, when he ſaith iii. <hi>Galat.</hi> 24. <hi>The Law was our School-maſter to bring us to Chriſt:</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63800:6"/> proceeds in the next Chapter of that Epiſtle to illuſtrate this moſt elegantly from the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Abraham;</hi> who had two Sons (iv. <hi>Gal.</hi> 22.) the one by a Bond-maid, the other by a Free-woman: the firſt of which was born after the Fleſh, but the other was by Promiſe. <hi>Which things</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>v.</hi> 24.) <hi>are an Allegory: for theſe are the two Covenants, or Teſtaments;</hi> the one from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> which gendreth to Bondage; the other from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> or <hi>Sion,</hi> which is free, the Mother of us all.</p>
               <p>Where we learn theſe two things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That even in ſuch hiſtorical Relations as theſe, the Apoſtles read diviner things; which they ſaw there lye hid and concealed. For that's his meaning, when he ſaith, theſe things are <hi>an Allegory; aliud portendentia</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> expounds it <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>L. V. contra Marcionem,</hi> c. 4.</note>) a ſpeech about another mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, portending ſomething elſe than at firſt ſight appears. For he clearly diſcerned, that under the Names and Actions of <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Hagar, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> God was pleaſed to foreſhadow what He intended to do in future times, both at the giving of the Law, and when He ſent his Son to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> we learn, that as thoſe two Wives of very different Condition, had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63800:6"/> but one and the ſame Husband, who was the Father of thoſe two Children: So the two Teſtaments, the Old and the New, which were repreſented by thoſe two Women, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to one and the ſame God; who brings forth and breeds up his Children under vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſpenſations, but is the Father of all thoſe who lived piouſly under the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as well as of thoſe who live ſo under the New.</p>
               <p>This is the neceſſary Conſequence of the Apoſtles Diſcourſe. If thoſe two Wives and their Children were an <hi>Allegorie</hi> of the two Teſtaments, and of thoſe who were born and bred under them; then as thoſe two Children had the ſame Father though diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Mothers, ſo the two Teſtaments have the ſame Original; though they be Diſpenſations as different as the Bond-woman and the Free. There cannot be a more evident Confutation of the falſe Principles of theſe Men, than this Obſervation of the Apoſtle. Who in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Epiſtle (i. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1, 2.) calls himſelf <hi>an Apoſtle, ſeparated unto the Goſpel of God, which he had promiſed afore by his Prophets in the Holy Scriptures, concerning his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> And in the entrance of the Epiſtle
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63800:7"/> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> openly avows, that the ſame <hi>God who at ſundry times and in divers manners ſpake unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpoken unto us by his Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I ſhall not trouble you any further in ſo manifeſt a buſineſs; having thus far obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my end; which was to ſhew that the Hiſtorical Books are not unuſeful, but more ſerviceable than many imagine; not merely becauſe they relate the wonderful Providence of God over that People for whoſe uſe they were firſt written, in bleſſing them when they were faithful to him, and puniſhing them when they revolted from him; but becauſe they contain many ſecret Repreſentations of things belonging to the Perſon and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>The next part of their wicked Doctrine was, that the Old Teſtament <hi>did not belong to Chriſtians, but only to the Jews.</hi> This <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichee</hi> (againſt whom St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> wrote XXXIII. Books) endeavoured to perſwade by his Natural Eloquence and ſmooth way of ſpeaking (for which he was famous <note n="*" place="margin">See St. <hi>Auſt. Confeſſions,</hi> L. V. cap. 3. &amp; 6.</note>) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any judgment or reaſon at all. For it is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63800:7"/> directly confuted by the words of my Text; as if the Apoſtle intended to anticipate ſuch an Objection, and prevent the entrance of this extravagant Conceit into any bodies mind. The abſurdity of which appears alſo farther from hence; that the Promiſes made in the Old Teſtament belong to us Chriſtians, who are therefore concerned in the Teſtament it ſelf. Which is a Conſideration to which St. <hi>Paul</hi> directs us in the Epiſtle for this day; a little below my Text: <hi>v. 8. Now I ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt was a Miniſter of the Circumciſion;</hi> ſent, that is, to preach the Goſpel unto the <hi>Jews; for the truth of God;</hi> to juſtifie, that is, the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God who promiſed to ſend him, as it follows; <hi>to confirm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Promiſes made unto the Fathers;</hi> that is, make good thoſe Promiſes he had paſſed to them in ancient time; among which this was the chief, that he would ſend a Perſon into the World in the fulneſs of time, in whom all Nations ſhould be bleſſed. So it follows, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10, &amp;c. <hi>And that the Gentiles might glorifie God for his Mercy; as it is written, For this cauſe I will confeſs to thee among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and ſing unto thy Name. And again he ſaith, Rejoyce ye Gentiles, with his People. And again, Praiſe the Lord all ye Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And again
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63800:8"/> Pſaias ſaith, He that ſhall riſe to reign over the Gentiles, in him ſhall the Gentiles truſt.</hi> All which places of the Old Scriptures are alledged to ſhew, that though this was the grand Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that God had expreſſely obliged himſelf by Promiſes to their Fathers to ſend his Son Chriſt to them; of which Promiſes the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> i. e. People of other Nations were wholly ignorant, and knew not a ſyllable of this Grace: yet God intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ſo mercifull as to make all the world partakers of thoſe Promiſes which the <hi>Jews</hi> alone had recorded in their holy Books. Which the Apoſtle proves was agreeable to the Books themſelves wherein theſe Promiſes were contained. For they predicted that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo ſhould <hi>rejoyce</hi> in God, and <hi>praiſe</hi> him, and <hi>ſing</hi> unto his Name, becauſe Chriſt the Son of <hi>David</hi> ſhould <hi>reign</hi> over them as well as his Ancient People, and they ſhould place their <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>truſt</hi> in him. This he urges from more places of the Old Scriptures (as well of the <hi>Law of Moſes, as of the Prophets and Pſalms,</hi> as you will find if you take the pains to examine them) than he alledges for the proof of any one thing whatſoever; for this great reaſon, That the Gentiles might
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63800:8"/> be the more confirmed and ſettled in the Faith of the Goſpel, when they ſaw it was brought to them not by the Will of Man, but by the good pleaſure and Counſel of God, long before predicted in the Holy Scriptures of Truth.</p>
               <p>This is a plain demonſtration how much we are concerned in the Scriptures written aforetime; whoſe true Learning the ſame Apoſtle ſhews in another place, is not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the <hi>Jews,</hi> but only by Chriſtians; to whom the Grace of God is tranſlated, which is taken away from the other, till they alſo Believe on Chriſt Jeſus. Read 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> iii. 14, 15. where he ſaith, their Minds are blinded, and that they have a Veil upon them in the reading of the Old Teſtament: <hi>Which veil is done away in Chriſt,</hi> i. e. when men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſtians. <hi>But even unto this day, when Moſes is read, the veil is upon their heart: never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs when it</hi> (their heart) <hi>ſhall turn to the Lord</hi> (our Saviour Chriſt) <hi>the veil ſhall be taken away;</hi> and not till then. Which is an evidence that we have more benefit by the Scriptures writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten aforetime, than the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, till they alſo turn Chriſtians; and abundantly confirms that pithy ſaying of <hi>Tertullian</hi> (which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63800:9"/> comprehends all that need be ſaid in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,) <hi>Novum Teſtamentum in Vetere latet, Vetus Teſtamentum in Novo patet;</hi> the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament lyes hid in the Old; and the Old Teſtament is revealed and diſcovered in the New. And ſo I have done with the <hi>Second</hi> Cavil of theſe men againſt the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>The <hi>third</hi> part of their impious Doctrine about this matter was, That the Scriptures written aforetime were <hi>unprofitable for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of our Faith.</hi> Which is directly againſt the whole Scope of the Apoſtle in this place, and is confuted in expreſs terms by our Bleſſed Lord himſelf in ſeveral places of the laſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Goſpel according to S. <hi>Luke.</hi> Where ſpeaking of his Paſſion to two of his Diſciples, <hi>v.</hi> 25. 27. He upbraided them that they were ſuch Fools, and ſlow of heart to believe what the Prophets had ſpoken: <hi>and beginning at Moſes and all the Prophets, he expounded unto them in all the Scriptures, the things concerning himſelf.</hi> And not long after appearing to all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and eating with them, he ſaid (<hi>v.</hi> 44.) <hi>Theſe are the words which I ſpake unto you while I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63800:9"/> was yet with you, that all things muſt be fulfilled which were written in the Law of Moſes, and in the Prophets, and in the Pſalms concerning me.</hi> And then opening their underſtanding, that they might underſtand the Scripture, he ſaid, <hi>Thus it is written, and thus it behoved Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe again the third day,</hi> &amp;c. So abominably falſe it is, which thoſe Hereticks were wont to aſſert, that in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there was no Teſtimony concerning Chriſt. They are the words of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> as they are reported by St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> xii. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Fauſt</hi> c. 1, 2.</note>: and may well make us wonder how any men that were called by his Name ſhould arrive at ſuch a boldneſs, as to contradict Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who proved all things concerning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of thoſe ancient Books.</p>
               <p>But this it is to be proud and ſelf-conceited; to be forward to teach <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid. S.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, Confeſſ. l. v. c. 5.</note>, before men have learnt; to be addicted to a Sect, and to love to contradict; to be engaged early in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and then to ſtop ones ears againſt the means of Information; to be carryed away with a ſtrong antipathy to that, which men do not underſtand, nor have duly weighed and conſidered. Againſt all which Vices the Scriptures caution us ſufficiently, if we mean
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63800:10"/> to underſtand them: telling us plainly, that if we will not purge our ſelves from ſuch ill humours, we ſhall become vain in our Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and our fooliſh hearts will be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Witneſs the fooliſh exception that theſe men took to the Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe they repreſented God, according to their Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as deſirous of the Blood and Fat of Beaſts, which he required to be offered in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to him. Whereas nothing is more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, than that God himſelf by the Prophets (who ſpake as they acknowledge by the ſame Spirit that <hi>Moſes</hi> did) utterly diſclaimed any delight or ſatisfaction that he took in mere Sacrifices, though never ſo numerous and coſtly: Nay, proteſts that he abominated them, if they were not brought to his Altar with a pious mind, and accompanyed with actions of Juſtice and Charity. Which makes it apparent, that it was the heart of the Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to which he had regard; and that he lookt upon theſe, but as outward teſtimonies and ſignifications of a grateful Mind, or of a penitent heart, or of a Soul reſolved to devote it ſelf to his ſervice.</p>
               <p>I need not adde, that they were manifeſt Figures and Preſignifications of the great Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63800:10"/> of Chriſt Jeſus, who hath purged away our ſins by his own blood: nor take any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pains to confute theſe audacious Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks from other places of Holy Writ. I will rather take to task a little another ſort of men, no leſs bold and ſhameleſs; who would fain be thought the greateſt Enemies to Hereticks, of all men in the world. I mean them of the <hi>Romiſh Religion,</hi> who notwithſtanding their glorious pretences, would be heartily glad if this Propoſition could be made good, That the Scriptures written aforetime, are unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the Confirmation of Points of Faith. For our Writers have ſo overpower'd them with Teſtimonies fetcht from thence, that they are not able to ſtand before us to defend the Prime Article of their preſent Faith; that Article which is the principal Cauſe of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> for whoſe ſake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all other Controverſies have been craftily kept on foot; I mean that of the Supremacy of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rome enim ſubjici, inde pendere, haec Veſtrae Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſumma eſt. <hi>Reſp. ad Tort. p.</hi> 81.</note>: Which we utterly confound by beginning at <hi>Moſes</hi> (to allude to the words before mentioned) and ſo ſhewing through all the Scriptures written aforetime, that, <hi>He,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Aſa,</hi> and <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> and <hi>Hezekias,</hi> and <hi>Joſias,</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63800:11"/> the Prieſts and the whole Tribe of <hi>Levi:</hi> 
                  <q>Ordering the time of their waiting and officiating in their Courſes; appointing Judges in Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, and ſetting Preſidents over thoſe Judges; taking away abuſes and corruptions in Religion; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the <hi>Ark</hi> to be removed from one place to another, and calling the people by their Proclamations, to come and meet there before the Lord; requiring the Prieſts to read the Book of the Law, and to reduce things to a Conformity with it; renewing the Covenant of <hi>Moſes</hi> for Reformation of Religion; making Miſſions of Prieſts into ſuch parts of the Countrey, as they ſaw need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their aſſiſtance; and (to ſay no more) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the High-Prieſt himſelf, and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him from his Office.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now what ſay our Adverſaries to all this? Truly, after many other poor ſhifts, they are at laſt driven thus far to ſide with the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees,</hi> as to ſay, that theſe things belong not to us: for that Authority which was in Kings under the Old Teſtament, is now tranſlated (if you will believe thoſe Doctors) unto the Prieſts under the New. But what man of ſenſe can entertain this wild fancy, that Kings
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63800:11"/> under the Government of Chriſt, are in a worſe Condition than they were in under the Diſcipline of <hi>Moſes?</hi> Or that Chriſt ſhould ſingle out Kings of all other men, to be inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to them, and deprive them of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer rights; when he left every body elſe in the very ſame eſtate wherein he found them? Was this our Saviours buſineſs (when he came <hi>to reign over the Gentiles,</hi>) to ſtrip their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Prerogatives, and leſſen their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority over their Subjects? How deteſtable would the Apoſtles have been, if they had broached this Doctrine, when they went out to convert the World? Or ſhall we be ſo impious as to think, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> equivocated, or had ſome mental Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when he Commanded <hi>every Soul</hi> in the Roman Church <hi>to be ſubject to the higher Powers?</hi> Mark, I beſeech you; it is upon the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that he preſſes this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (Chapter xiii. of this Epiſtle,) more than upon any other Church whatſoever: as if he foreſaw there would be an Apoſtaſie among them from this Faith. <hi>Let every Soul</hi> be ſubject: <hi>though thou beeſt an Apoſtle</hi> (and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> I hope was never great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than ſo) <hi>though an Evangeliſt, though a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63800:12"/> or whatſoever thou beeſt, thou muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject:</hi> as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> (whoſe words theſe are) faithfully expounds the Apoſtles honeſt meaning.</p>
               <p>And ſo Chriſtian Princes long after his time, underſtood him; and did not fear both to aſſume this Authority, and to juſtifie it when they had done ſo, after the ſame manner that we do, by the Example of the Kings that ruled over the People of God before the Coming of Chriſt. Witneſs, to name one for all, <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; a Prince as great in Eccleſiaſtical Policy, as in Feats of Arms: who, in his Preface to his <hi>Capitulary,</hi> tells the Clergy of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, <q>That he had ſent his Deputies to them; that they by his Authority, might, together with them, correct what ſtood in need of amendment; according to the Example of the godly King <hi>Joſias,</hi> who endeavoured, ſaith he, to reſtore the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which God had given him to the Service of the true God; by going about it, by correcting and admoniſhing it, as we read in the xxiii. Chapter of the Second Book of the <hi>Kings.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And they had been very much to blame if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63800:12"/> they had not taken this pains. For as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> admirably ſpeaks in a Sermon of his, recorded by one of the writers of his Life * <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Georgius Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrius. <hi>Tom. Ult. p.</hi> 265.</note> 
                  <hi>The Care appertaining to Kings is not ſo much about War, as about the Church; not ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Political Affairs, as about the Church:</hi> with whoſe Preſervation and Safety God having been pleaſed to intruſt them; he expects they ſhould be as angry with thoſe who would A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterate his Worſhip therein ſetled, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was with <hi>Aaron,</hi> when he had made the Golden Calf. That very example is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſhew the Authority, which the Civil Magiſtrates have in matters of Religion. With which they ought not to part, no more than they would with their Crowns: nor to ſuffer their people to be deprived of theſe Holy Books wherein they may read theſe things; and thereby be ſo throughly poſſeſt with a ſenſe of their high Authority, that they may never be Debauched from their Duty. But of that more preſently.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>Let us firſt hear what the next exception of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63800:13"/> the <hi>Manichees</hi> was aginſt the Scriptures written aforetime; which they ſaid were <hi>unprofitable to teach men good manners; nay, were deſtructive and contrary to them.</hi> There are two parts you ſee of this wicked ſuggeſtion, the firſt of which is ſo directly confuted by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in another place, that one would think theſe men never read the New Teſtament at all, nor the Old for any other end, than to carp at it and frame Objections againſt it. For in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> iii. 16. he expreſsly ſaies that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>All Scripture</hi> (ſpeaking of the <hi>Old,</hi> for not much of the <hi>New</hi> was then extant) <hi>given by inſpiration of God, is profitable for Doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in Righteouſneſs.</hi> Upon which words you may be pleaſed to take this ſhort gloſs. All Holy Learning conſiſts in being wiſe and in being good; in acquiring of both which, the Scriptures, being Divinely inſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, give us ſingular aſſiſtance. As for the <hi>firſt,</hi> (Chriſtian Wiſdom) it conſiſts in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Truth, and in rejecting Falſhood. Now behold how profitable the Scriptures are in both regards: For they are profitable <hi>for Doctrine</hi> which is teaching the Truth; and <hi>for reproof,</hi> which is confuting the <hi>falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood</hi> of Error. And then for the <hi>Second</hi> (learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63800:13"/> to be good) that conſiſts of two parts more as the Prophets inſtruct us, to ceaſe to do Evil, and to learn to do Well. To both which ends alſo the Apoſtle affirms the Holy Scripture is profitable: <hi>for correction</hi> that is, when we do amiſs; and <hi>for inſtruction in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> to make us do better. And that (I may add) not only by its Precepts, but by its Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: examples which ſtrongly excite and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us to our duty; and which mightily deter and withold us from doing wickedly. I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mention ſome of the latter ſort, which are drawn up to my hand by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the next Epiſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> x. where he ſets before that Church the example of the ancient <hi>Iſraelites; with many of whom God was not well pleaſed, for they were overthrown in the Wilderneſs,</hi> after he had brought them out of the bondage of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> v. 5. And leſt they ſhould think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unconcern'd in ſuch ſtories, he adds, v. 6. <hi>Now theſe things were our examples; to the intent that we ſhould not Luſt after evil things as they alſo Luſted. Neither be ye Idolaters as were ſome of them; as it is written. The people ſat down to Eat and Drink, and roſe up to Play. Neither let us commit Fornication, as ſome of them commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and fell in one day three and twenty thouſand.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63800:14"/> Neither let us tempt Chriſt, as ſome of them tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and were deſtroyed of Serpents. Neither mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur ye, as ſome of them alſo murmured, and were deſtroyed of the deſtroyer. Now all theſe things hapned unto them for Examples; and they are written for our admonition upon whom the ends of the World are come.</hi> So he concludes, after the ſame manner as he began, this pathetical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: Which we ought to lay to heart, and apply to our ſelves as much, as if he had told us in other words (which are but an explication of theſe,) <q>I would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have you abuſe your ſelves with falſe Opinions, and therefore do not imagine, I beſeech you, that theſe things, which were done ſo long ago, do not belong to you; or that the Sins I have mentioned are not ſo deadly now as they were then: becauſe thoſe dreadful Miracles are ceaſed, and you ſee no devouring Fire, no Earth gaping to ſwallow you up, no fiery Serpents, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Angel ſmiting Multitudes dead in an inſtant. For <hi>all theſe things,</hi> that is, theſe Puniſhments, <hi>hapned unto them,</hi> or were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon the old <hi>Iſraelites, for Examples</hi> (or for <hi>Types,</hi> as it is in the Margin) of that Puniſhment which (notwithſtanding Gods
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63800:14"/> wonderful Grace to us, in delivering us out of a worſe Slavery than that of <hi>Egypt,</hi>) ſhall fall more heavily upon us than upon them, if we be diſobedient to him. The reaſon is, becauſe we are a Diviner and more Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual People, of whom they were but the Types and Figures; and therefore can leſs expect to be indulged in ſuch wickedneſs as they ſmarted ſo ſorely for: but ought to be warned by their ſad Examples, and to look upon theſe things as recorded <hi>for our admonition;</hi> that we may learn, <hi>i. e.</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of ſuch ſins as thoſe now mentioned, which are far more provoking now than they were in former times.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But to this thoſe <hi>Manichees</hi> object (as we find in the formentioned <hi>Fauſtus</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>L. XXII. cap. 1.</hi> contra Fauſt.</note>) that there are abundance of evil Examples in the Old Teſtament; which, they fancy, juſtifies the <hi>Second</hi> part of this Propoſition, That the Old Scriptures <hi>teach things contrary to good Manners.</hi> For we find in the Lives of the Patriarchs and Prophets, ſome things, not only blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but very wicked; as the Drunkenneſs of <hi>Noah,</hi> the Inceſt of <hi>Lot,</hi> the Murder and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of <hi>David;</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63800:15"/>
               <p>To which I have a plain and true Anſwer; that even from the recording of theſe things we may learn very much; if we will read ſuch parts of the Holy Scripture, as we ought to do all the reſt, with a piouſly diſpoſed Mind. I ſhall mention <hi>four</hi> things, that thoſe Examples teach us, if we be inclined to make a good uſe of them. 1. Something <hi>to confirm our Faith.</hi> 2. Something <hi>to guide the Courſe of our Lives.</hi> 3. Something <hi>to preſerve us from Sin.</hi> And, 4. Something <hi>to recover us,</hi> in caſe we fall into it.</p>
               <p>I. Firſt, I ſay, they may ſerve very much to confirm our Faith; and to make us leſs doubt of the truth of the Hiſtory of the Bible. Which it is manifeſt was not invented for the Honour and Credit of the Jewiſh Nation; becauſe it faithfully relates even the ſouleſt blemiſhes of their Noble Anceſtors: which, if it had been indited by their private ſpirit, ſhould have been carefully concealed. The Holy Books may be compared to a pure Looking-glaſs; which ſhews not only the Beauty, the lovely Features and comely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions of thoſe Perſons that are repreſented in it, but all their Spots and Deformities. They flatter no mans Perſon, but praiſe all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63800:15"/> the Actions, even of bad men, which are worthy of Commendation; and reprehend all that are otherwiſe, even in the good and vertuous. And therefore,</p>
               <p>II. We may learn ſomething from theſe Examples for the guidance of our Lives, and reforming our Manners: which is to follow Precepts, not Examples. For Examples then alone are imitable, when they are conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thoſe Rules, which make them good Examples. The beſt of men may erre; and therefore we are not ſo much to mind, which Way they go, as which way they <hi>ought</hi> to go. For there is a Rule, by which they are as much bound to walk, as we; from which if they ſwerve, we are to leave them, and ſtick to that. For againſt a Rule, no Examples can be a ſufficient Warrant. They are ſo far from having any ſuch Authority; that we are to examine, whether the Rule it ſelf by which holy men heretofore governed their actions, was a General Rule; or only Particular. For if it was ſpecial and perſonal, there it muſt reſt; and the Example of thoſe who obeyed it muſt not carry it any further. If it do; we act by our own private Authority, and apply to our ſelves things that belonged pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63800:16"/> to other men: and ſo, doing ſuch things as they did, without ſuch a Warrant, involve our ſelves in a Guilt of which they were innocent. In ſhort, they that do not live regularly themſelves, cannot be a Rule to others.</p>
               <p>III. But there is ſtill a good uſe, which we may and ought to make of ſuch irregular Examples. From which we may learn ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that will be a Preſervative from Sin, not an Incentive to it: and that is, deep Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; a pious Fear, with due Caution and Circumſpection; Diſtruſt of our ſelves and of our own ſtrength; with earneſt Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to God for his gracious Aſſiſtance; and a lively Faith and Confidence in him, as our beſt Security. For if ſuch great, ſuch Holy men fell, and fell ſo foully, and bruiſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo ſorely; have not we juſt cauſe to be jealous of our ſelves, and to live in a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fear, leſt we alſo be tempted, and carried away from our ſtedfaſtneſs? As we ſhall be moſt certainly; unleſs we be careful and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, watchful and diligent; adhering cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God by a conſtant vigorous ſenſe of him preſerved in our Minds: which we ſhould
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63800:16"/> learn to awaken and quicken by frequent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon ſuch lamentable Examples of humane weakneſs and frailty.</p>
               <p>IV. From which alſo we may learn, in caſe we ſhould be ſo unhappy as to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, and fall into Sin, ſomething that may help to recover and reſtore us. Which is, not to deſpair of Gods Mercy; but to hope, by unfeigned Repentance, and greater care for the future, we may obtain a Pardon, and be accepted again into his favour, as they were; ſome of whoſe Repentance is as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, in the ancient Story, as their ſin.</p>
               <p>This is the uſe we ought to make of ſuch parts of the Holy Writings: By which, if we will encourage our ſelves to be bold to do wickedly, becauſe ſuch pious men fell into ſin; or to preſume of Gods Mercy, though we continue in it, and do not riſe again by Repentance; or take occaſion to deſpair of doing better, becauſe of the deplorable weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Humane Nature; we muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to God, for ſuch perverſe abuſe of his Holy Word; which contains no ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples among all thoſe that it propounds to our Imitation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63800:17"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>There is one thing more remaining, which if they could have made good, would have been an Objection indeed; and that is, That <hi>the Old Teſtament oppoſes and contradicts the New.</hi> About this <hi>Adimantus</hi> a <hi>Manichee</hi> the Maſter of <hi>Fauſtus</hi> wrote a whole Book: but the Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he alledges are ſo frivolous, that they are ſcarce worth the confuting. I will mention one, becauſe it may ſuggeſt ſomething for our Learning, whereby you may judge of all the reſt. In the Old Teſtament we read, that if any man hurt his Neighbour, he was bound to ſatisfie to the full for the damage done, by ſuffering the very ſame himſelf; <hi>Eye for Eye, Tooth for Tooth, Hand for Hand, and Foot for Foot,</hi> &amp;c. xxi. <hi>Exod.</hi> 24, 25. But our Saviour ſayes in the New Teſtament, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on thy right cheek, turn to him the other alſo. And if a man take away thy Coat, let him have thy Cloak alſo.</hi> v. Matth. 39, 40. Are not theſe things oppoſite? I anſwer with St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who hath made an excellent Reply to this Cavil, both in his Book againſt <hi>Adimantus</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Cap. VIII.</note>, and againſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> 
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Lib. XIX. cap. 25.</note>; to this effect. Theſe things diſcover no contrariety
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63800:17"/> in the two Teſtaments; but only the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent degrees of their perfection. For there being <hi>two</hi> degrees of Meekneſs and Forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; the <hi>firſt</hi> that the Grief of the injured perſon do not provoke him to ſeek a revenge, beyond the meaſure of the damage that was done him; the <hi>ſecond</hi> that the injured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon pardon and paſs by the whole wrong, though grievous to him, with a peaceable and appeaſed mind: the Old Teſtament, as leſs perfect, preſerved carnal men within the bounds of the firſt degree of Patience, and kept them from extending their revenge too far; but the New Teſtament, as more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, advances ſpiritual men to the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent degree of a plenary remiſſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any revenge at all.</p>
               <p>So that even from ſuch paſſages as theſe we learn, you ſee, how much we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to God, for a greater abundance of his Grace, than he beſtowed in former times. Which ſhould raiſe us, as to a greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of gratefull Love to him, ſo, to a more excellent degree of Piety and Vertue; to which He intends to improve us by this New
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63800:18"/> Revelation he hath made of his good will to us in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>And that is part of the uſe we may make of what hath been ſaid.</p>
               <p>If we may learn ſo much from thoſe Books which were written aforetime, in the dayes of old, before the Coming of our Saviour into the World: what may we do from thoſe which were written ſince his appearing; who is the very Wiſdom of God, the only begotten Son, which is in the boſom of the Father, and hath declared him unto us? They preſcribe us a more rational Service of Almighty God; and raiſe us to a higher pitch of brotherly Love; and teach us greater Purity of Body and Mind; and preſs all theſe upon us by more perfect Examples, and by more excellent Motives; eſpecially by the bleſſed hope of Immortal Life; which if we have any ſenſe of our own deareſt Intereſt, we ought <hi>to embrace and to hold faſt</hi> (as it is in the <hi>Collect</hi> for this day) being willing to do and to ſuffer any thing that God would have us, rather than loſe ſo great, ſo incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable a good: Which the more we think of, the more it attracts us to it, and holds
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63800:18"/> us faſt in its embraces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as a perfect ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all our deſires.</p>
               <p>But from that Conſideration we may take occaſion alſo to reflect, how injurious they are to Chriſtian People (to whom God hath been ſo bountiful) who forbid them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their leave to meddle with theſe holy Books; wherein their Hope of Immortal Life is contained: Nay, make a ſevere In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition after them that dare be ſo bold as to have, in their own Language, a Copy of the Will and Teſtament of their bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, (or if you pleaſe ſo to call it) of that Deed of Grace whereby he hath conveyed to them the Eternal Inheritance. S. <hi>Peter</hi> indeed, 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> ii. 9. honours all Chriſtians ſo much as to call them <hi>a choſen Generation, a royal Prieſthood, a holy Nation, a peculiar People:</hi> But they, who pretend to ſucceed him, uſe them as if they were no better than baſe Slaves, nay vile Beaſts; who are not fit to be entruſted with this Liberty, and enjoy the Priviledge of hearing God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſpeaking to them in his holy Goſpel. No, there is a Caution in the Law, ſaith <hi>Innocent</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63800:19"/> the third, <hi>that if a Beaſt touch the Mountain, it ſhall be ſtoned:</hi> from thence concluding that the ſimple and unlearned ſhould not meddle with the Subtilty of Holy Writ. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we agree with him, that from all Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and curious Inquiries, every body ought to abſtain: But we are not ſatisfied that He or any man elſe hath Authority, to compare the People of God to Beaſts. As others among them have done in a moſt ſcornfull manner; when they prove from hence that the People muſt not read the Scriptures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we muſt <hi>not caſt that which is holy to Dogs, nor throw Pearls before Swine.</hi> This is very rude Language; but the Authors are well known who have ſpoken thus contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſly of the Flock of Chriſt (whom <hi>he</hi> calls <hi>his Sheep,</hi> but they call <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Swine</hi>) and thereby debaſed Chriſtians below the moſt blockiſh <hi>Jews,</hi> who did never ſo abuſe their Holy Books, as to forfeit the liberty of Reading them; which they challenge and uſe as a Right belonging to all at this very day. What Reaſon can be given for ſuch unworthy. Treatment of thoſe whom the Apoſtles ſo highly eſteemed, and ſpake
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63800:19"/> of with ſo much reſpect, but only this; that they ſee there is ſuch a manifeſt diſagreement between them and the Scriptures, that their Errours would be in danger to be detected by the ſimpleſt people, if they ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to come into this light?</p>
               <p>And here let me note, that ſuch guides are faln into a contrary errour, to that of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees,</hi> of which I have now treated. They do not ſay, that the Books of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> are ſuperfluous and unneceſſary; but that they, and the Books of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> to boot, are defective and imperfect: and that their defects muſt be ſupplied, out of ſuch Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as they propound to our belief. But among oppoſite Errours, the cauſes of erring are commonly the ſame, as the great Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher obſerves; and is very true in this caſe. For though there be ſeveral wayes the Enemy of mankind hath taken, to compaſs his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of bringing the Scriptures into diſgrace, and ſetting up the inventions of men inſtead of them, or in Conjunction with them; yet the reaſon ſtill is one and the ſame: which is, that the holy Scriptures are not for his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63800:20"/> turn; he cannot deceive men ſo eaſily, if they keep cloſe to this hold. Which is a ſtrong hold indeed; and comprehends all that we need to <hi>know,</hi> or <hi>believe,</hi> or <hi>do:</hi> to which nothing need, nothing ought to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as neceſſary to our Salvation. According to that peremptory reſolution of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his third Book againſt <hi>Petilians</hi> Letters, (Chapt. vi.) <hi>Whether it be about Chriſt, or about his Church, or about any other thing whatſoever, that belongs to Faith or to our Life, I will not ſay we (who are by no means to be compared with him that ſaid,</hi> licet nos, <hi>although we) but as he preſently adds, if an Angel from Heaven ſhall declare to you any thing, beſides that which you have received</hi> in Scripturis Legalibus &amp; Evangelicis, <hi>in the Scriptures of the Law and the Goſpel, let him be accurſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which let me add this notable ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of S. <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great, who comprehends all that I have ſaid in a few words, in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Faith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom. II. pag.</hi> 251.</note>. <hi>It is a manifeſt falling of Faith, and may be juſtly charged with Pride; either to reject any thing that is written; or to introduce, and bring in over and above, any thing that is not written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the ancient Catholick Doctrine;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63800:20"/> which it is the Intereſt (let me take the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſay) as well as the Duty-of-Chriſtian Kings and Princes, above all other men, to aſſert and maintain. For by theſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Books their Authority is as ſtrongly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported; as by the pretended Traditions of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church it is notoriouſly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and ſubverted. Upon which account it is a point of their greateſt Wiſdom, not only to keep theſe Books in their Peoples hands; but to encourage, nay command the conſcientious reading of them; that they may there learn how plainly they are taught, and how Religiouſly they are bound to fear, honour and obey their Sovereigns, even though they were Pagans; much more when they are Chriſtians. Of which Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty if they ſuffer their People to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, they ſhall ſoon be taught that they owe no further reſpect to their Princes, than it pleaſes the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to allow them. Who from the Dignity of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Biſhop and Paſtor of Souls, is raiſed to be a Worldly Monarch, above all Kings and Emperours; by ſewing ſeveral patches and ſhreds to the ancient Chriſtian Doctrine,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63800:21"/> under the Name of <hi>Traditions.</hi> For nothing is more apparent in Hiſtory than this; that as the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>'s <hi>Greatneſs</hi> increaſed, ſo <hi>Traditions</hi> were ſtill more and more mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed; which in proceſs of time were more recommended than the Scriptures themſelves, and more Religiouſly obſerved.</p>
               <p>There is another Reaſon alſo, why Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould keep the Holy Books open before their Subjects eyes, and ſuffer no Man to ſhut them and ſeal them up: Becauſe it plainly appears by them, that their Perſons and Office are Sacred; not a mere humane Inſtitution, but the Ordinance of God, by whom Kings reign, and by vertue of whoſe Laws they demand Obedience. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this is taught by the Popes Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and will ſoon be obtruded for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, if the Holy Scriptures be laid aſide. <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> for inſtance, in his Book againſt <hi>Barclay,</hi> maintains, that their Power proceeds not from God, but is the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Man. Conformable to that memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Maxim of Father <hi>Binet,</hi> in a Diſcourſe of his with the famous <hi>Caſaubon</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt. ad Frontonem Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeum.</hi> p. 209.</note>, about
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63800:21"/> the buſineſs of <hi>Garnet</hi> (which he calls the Immortal God to witneſs is true) <hi>That it were better all Kings ſhould periſh, than the Seal of Confeſſion ſo much as once be violated; for the Authority of Kings is by Humane Right, but Confeſſion by Divine.</hi> Which ſounds ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridly in all true Chriſtian ears, that it is hard to find any thing more contrary to common Reaſon and to the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, among that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as <hi>Andraeas Caeſarienſis</hi> calls them <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> IV. <hi>in</hi> Apocalypſ.</note>) that cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſtupid Tribe of <hi>Manichees,</hi> whoſe Fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zies I have in part repreſented. But this is not a place to lay open this Myſtery of Iniquity; whereby Kings are almoſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thron'd, and manifeſtly deprived of that which aſſures their Crowns and their Lives; far more than the conſtant Guard of their Bodies, or the moſt powerful Armies they can raiſe. For though by thoſe they may ſtrike terror into their Subjects minds; it is only the Senſe of God that can frame their hearts to Obedience. Then the Fidelity of Subjects will be firm and unmovable, when it is incorporated into Piety, and account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a part of Religion; a neceſſary piece of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63800:22"/> that Service which we owe to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. For which end the Scriptures muſt lye open before the People; that there they may read their Duty, and have their Souls moulded into a Senſe of God; and not merely receive ſuch Impreſſions, as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of men ſhall be pleaſed to ſtamp upon them.</p>
               <p>I conclude all with thoſe Notable words of S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his <hi>Second</hi> Homily upon S. <hi>Matthew;</hi> where he juſtifies what I have ſaid, from the words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> before mentioned. <hi>It is a great fault in Chriſtian People, that they do not Read the Scriptures: but to think it is a needleſs and ſuperfluous thing to read them, is a far greater Crime. This is language of the Devils invention: for do you not hear what</hi> S. Paul <hi>ſayes? That theſe things were written for our Inſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God grant we may in ſuch wiſe hear, read, mark, learn and inwardly digeſt them, that we may bring forth Fruit with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and do our Duty ſo faithfully to Him, to our Sovereign, to one another,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63800:22"/> and to all men, that in the end we may attain Everlaſting Life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be given by us and by all others, all Honour, Glory and Praiſe, both now and for evermore.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
